Once again, for passengers traveling on Flight 1457 to Orlando...
Pasajeros del vuelo 1457 a Orlando...
please take advantage of the boarding bag-check announcement.
...estיn al tanto del anuncio de su puerta de embarque.
You'll pick it up at baggage claim in Orlando.
Ya lo recogerבs en reclamaciףn de equipaje en Orlando.
It's a really full flight today.
El vuelo de hoy va completo.
- Hey. - Yeah, Jon Neal here.
- Hola. - Habla Jon Neal.
You just had sex with me in a hotel and left without saying goodbye.
Te acostaste conmigo y te fuiste sin despedirte.
Yeah, it ended up being delayed, so.... Sorry, I was panicking.
Sם, y el vuelo se atrasף. Perdףn, me entrף el pבnico.
Well, if I don't get to see you again...
Si no vuelvo a verte...
I just wanted to say it was nice to see you again.
...querםa decirte que me dio gusto verte.
Yeah, it was nice to see you too.
A mם tambiיn me dio gusto verte.
Um, and listen, use that other e-mail I gave you...
Oye, usa el otro correo electrףnico que te di...
because that's the only secure one, okay?
...porque ese es seguro, ¿estב bien?
Okay.
Estב bien.
You all right?
¿Estבs bien?
Yeah, I'm just....
Sם. Es...
I'm just jet-lagged. I'm tired.
Es el cambio de horario.
You should go home and get some rest. Hong Kong's a long way.
Vete a tu casa y descansa. Hong Kong estב muy lejos.
Attention passengers on Flight 5228...
- Atenciףn, pasajeros del vuelo 5228... - Espera.
- Oh, wait. - to Minneapolis.
...a Minneapolis.
Is that you?
¿Es tu vuelo?
Yep, that's me. They're calling my flight.
Sם. Estבn anunciando mi vuelo.
All right. Well, look, I'm really glad you called.
Me dio mucho gusto que me llamaras.
- Thanks. Bye. - Bye.
- Gracias. Adiףs. - Adiףs.
Please have your boarding passes out and ready.
Tengan listas sus tarjetas de embarque.
Thanks.
Gracias.
- Good morning, Roger. - Hey.
- Buenos dםas, Roger. - Hola.
So you really kicked ass in that football pool, huh?
Nos aplastaste en las apuestas de futbol.
You need to give up on your Lions. Pick with your head, not your heart.
Sם. Deje de apostarle a los Leones.
Yeah, thank you for the tip.
Gracias por el consejo.
- Yeah. Hey, hey. Hey, doc, uh-- - Yeah?
- Sם, oiga, doc. - ¿Sם?
I know you're busy. Uh-- I, uh--
Sי que estב ocupado...
- You got a second? - Sure.
- ¿Tiene un segundo? - Sם.
- I got a medical question. - Mm-hm.
Tengo una pregunta mיdica.
- Uh, attention deficit thing. - ADHD?
- Algo de dיficit de atenciףn. - ¿TDAH?
- Yeah. - He been diagnosed yet?
- Sם. - ¿Ya lo diagnosticaron?
That's the thing. They want him to see someone.
Quieren que alguien lo vea.
I was wondering if you could take a look at him.
¿Usted podrםa verlo?
- I'm not really that kind of doctor. - Oh. I didn't know. I just thought--
- No soy esa clase de mיdico. - Sם, pensי que quizבs...
Maybe I can refer someone, though.
Quizב podrםa recomendarte a alguien.
- Yeah? - Yeah. It's treatable.
- ¿Sם? - Sם. Se puede tratar.
- Okay. - We'll find someone, have them take a look.
- Bien. - Encontraremos a alguien que lo vea.
- Shouldn't be a problem. - Okay.
- No serב un problema. - De acuerdo.
- All right. - Yup.
- Muy bien. - Sם.
- Thanks, doc. - You're welcome.
- Gracias, doc. - De nada.
Why doesn't anybody help him? Is he okay?
¿Nadie le va a ayudar? ¿Estב bien?
Read the posts.
Lee los comentarios.
Some say it was staged. An art project.
Dicen que era ensayado. Un proyecto de arte.
Some say the authorities wouldn't do an autopsy.
Dicen que el gobierno no quiso hacerle autopsia...
Covered it up.
...para encubrirlo.
- Covered what up? - We don't know.
- ¿Para encubrir quי? - No sabemos.
Maybe Minamata disease. You know, from mercury in the fish.
Quizבs sea mal de Minamata, del mercurio del pescado.
There have been outbreaks in the past. Fishing industry suppresses it.
Ha habido brotes. La industria de la pesca los encubre.
- "Industrial disease." - Yeah, but it's just one man.
- "Enfermedad industrial". - Sם, pero es un solo hombre.
- We don't know what happened. - Just one man on video.
- No sabemos lo que pasף. - Es un solo hombre en el video.
Not everyone has the foresight to die in front of a camera.
Me preocupan los que no mueren frente a una cבmara.
The ones we don't see worry me.
Ellos mandan pescado a todo el mundo.
How many people read your paper over a plate of sushi?
¿Cuבnta gente come sushi?
Alan, we have almost no freelance budget anymore, and after H1--
No hay presupuesto para reportajes por honorarios...
You wait. A few days, this will be tweeted...
En unos dםas esto estarב en YouTube por todo el planeta.
- and YouTubed all over the planet. - We don't wanna be the paper that cries wolf.
No queremos dar una falsa alarma.
I'll show it to Hobart. He does our health stuff.
Hobart hace los reportajes de salud.
You're gonna give him my story? You're gonna give him my story, aren't you?
¿Le vas a dar mi reportaje? ¿Sם, verdad?
No, Alan, I'm trying to help you. It's just one man on a bus.
Te quiero ayudar. Es una sola vםctima.
- I taped this meeting. - We need more information than that.
- Grabי esta junta. - Necesitamos mבs informaciףn.
This story runs in the Chronicle, I will sue your ass.
Si sale el artםculo en el Chronicle, ¡te demandarי!
Great. Okay, bye, Alan. Don't call me anymore.
Adiףs, no me vuelvas a llamar.
Print media is dying, Lorraine.
La prensa escrita se estב muriendo, Lorraine.
It's dying. I'll save you a seat on the bus.
Se estב muriendo. Te apartarי un lugar en el autobתs.
Hi, I'm Mitch Emhoff. I'm Clark's stepdad. Clark Morrow.
Hola. Soy Mitch Emhoff, el padrastro de Clark Morrow.
He said he was feeling very warm in Mrs. Tatum's class.
Dijo que se sentםa muy caliente en clase.
I took his temperature again since I called. It was a touch over a hundred.
Le volvם a tomar la temperatura. Tiene un poco mבs de 39 grados.
Okay. Well, first his mom and now the mighty Clark, huh?
Primero su mamב y ahora el poderoso Clark.
All right, let's go get some soup for you and Mom.
Vamos a comprarte una sopa a ti y a tu mamב.
Hope you feel better, Clark, okay?
- Espero que te mejores, Clark, ¿sם? - Sם. Gracias.
Thattaboy.
Buen chico.
We're gonna beat this thing down by Turkey Day.
Vas a estar bien para el Dםa de Gracias.
I'm in Texas. I'll try it. I'll try anything once.
DֽA 4
Jory's going straight from the band trip to her mom's place.
Jory se irב directo a la casa de su mamב.
And my job interview got pushed to next week.
Pospusieron mi entrevista de trabajo una semana.
I'm not really sure what that means. Hopefully nothing.
No sי quי significa eso. Espero que nada.
Hey.
Oye.
My arm.
Mi brazo.
Come here, sit down, sit down, sit down. Watch your feet. Come on.
Ven, siיntate. Cuidado con los pies.
Come on. Come on, honey.
Ven, nena.
Okay, what happened? Did you take too much of that flu shit?
¿Tomaste demasiada medicina para la gripe?
Honey? Beth, Beth. Hey, hey, hey. Honey, honey.
¡Nena! ¡Beth! ¡Nena, nena!
Beth. Jesus. Jesus. Sweetheart. Sweetheart. Hey, Beth.
¡Beth! ¡Dios mםo! ¡Corazףn! ¡Corazףn! ¡Beth!
- Mom? - No, no, no. Uh-- Stay there, Clark. Don't--
- ¿Mamב? - No, no. Quיdate ahם, Clark.
Just go-- Go up to your room, honey. Uh....
Vete a tu cuarto.
Honey, honey.
¡Corazףn! ¡Corazףn!
- Beth. - Beth, can you hear me?
- Beth. - Beth. ¿Me oye?
My name's Dr. Arrington. You're in the hospital.
Soy el doctor Arrington. Estב en el hospital.
You had a seizure this morning, Beth.
Sufriף una convulsiףn.
- She have a history of seizures? - No, no, no.
- ¿Ya le habםa pasado? - No, no, no.
- Allergies? - Uh, I think she's allergic to penicillin.
- ¿Alguna alergia? - Creo que a la penicilina.
- She fall recently? Hit her head? - No, she came back from a trip--
- ¿Se golpeף la cabeza? - No. Regresף de un viaje y...
What about drugs? MDMA? Ecstasy?
- ¿Y drogas? ¿Metanfetaminas? ¿ֹxtasis? - No, no nos drogamos.
- Okay, let's get some help in here. - Jesus. Beth. Beth.
- ¡Necesito ayuda! - Cielos. Beth. Beth.
Sir, you have to go. You have to go.
- Tiene que salir. - ¡Pףnganle suero!
And give me 2 milligrams of Ativan, please.
Dos miligramos de Ativבn, por favor.
So, um, despite all our efforts, she failed to respond.
Entonces, a pesar de todos nuestros esfuerzos, no respondiף.
- Okay. - And her heart stopped...
- Sם... - Su corazףn se detuvo...
and unfortunately, she did die.
...y, desgraciadamente, falleciף.
Right.
Sם.
- I'm sorry, Mr. Emhoff. - I know this is hard to accept.
- Lo lamento, seסor Emhoff. - Yo sי que es difםcil de aceptar.
Okay. I mean, so can I go talk to her?
¿Puedo hablar con ella?
Mr. Emhoff, I'm sorry. Your wife is dead.
Seסor Emhoff, lo siento. Su esposa estב muerta.
I mean, I just saw her. We were just at home.
Acabo de verla. Estבbamos en casa.
Is there somebody that we can call?
¿Quiere que llamemos a alguien?
Someone who you think should be here with you?
¿Alguien que lo acompaסe?
I mean, we had dinner. We had pizza. She said she was jet-lagged.
Comimos pizza, se quejף del cambio de horario.
You mentioned that she was away. Hong Kong?
Usted dijo que estuvo de viaje. ¿Hong Kong?
We checked the latest bulletins.
Los boletines mבs recientes...
The only things there were measles and H1N1...
...solo mencionan sarampiףn y H1N1...
and this was not that.
...y no fue eso.
Then what was it?
¿Quי fue?
We don't always know.
No siempre sabemos.
I mean, some people get a disease and live, some get sicker and die.
Unos padecen de una enfermedad y viven, otros se mueren.
We're gonna have to notify the medical examiner...
Tenemos que avisar al Servicio de Salud.
and they may request an autopsy.
Quizב pidan una autopsia.
Or if you wish, we can order one.
Si quiere, nosotros pedimos una.
But I can't guarantee it's gonna tell you any more than I can.
Pero no le garantizo que nos aclare nada.
I mean, my best guess is that this was either meningitis or encephalitis...
Yo creo que fue meningitis o encefalitis.
and with encephalitis, we're in the dark a lot of the time.
De encefalitis casi nunca sabemos la causa.
If it was summer, I might say a bug bite, you know, West Nile.
Si fuera verano dirםa que fue un insecto, como el del Nilo Occidental.
- I don't know-- - Herpes can cause encephalitis.
- No sי... - El herpes puede causar encefalitis.
She didn't have herpes.
¡Ella no tenםa herpes!
- What are you talking about? - Okay.
- ¿De quי habla? - Entiendo.
What happened to her?
¿Quי le pasף?
- What happened to her? - Okay, okay.
- ¿Quי le pasף? - Calma, calma.
Mr. Emhoff, there are grief counselors...
Seסor Emhoff, tenemos especialistas en duelo...
who are very helpful with this sort of passing, okay?
...que ayudan mucho en fallecimientos como este.
You might find some resolution there.
Quizב le ayuden a sentirse mejor.
Now, I am sorry.
Lo lamento.
Hello?
¿Diga?
Hang up the phone and call 911 right now. Right now. 911.
¡Cuelga el telיfono y llama una ambulancia, ahora mismo!
He said he had a headache, so I put him to bed.
¡Le dolםa la cabeza y lo acostי!
I don't think he's breathing.
¡No sי si estב respirando!
Clark. Clark.
¡Clark! ¡Clark!
Oh, my God, is he dead?
¡Dios mםo! ¿Estב muerto?
What we are hearing from Beijing is that the outbreak is contained...
Pekםn informף que el brote estב contenido...
to the Chrysanthemum complex in Hong Kong.
...en el complejo Crisantemo de Hong Kong.
Two deaths and 10 suspected cases.
Dos muertes y diez infectados.
How are we defining "contained?"
¿Cףmo definimos "contenciףn"?
They're using the same protocols established for SARS.
Son los protocolos establecidos para el SARS.
They're quarantining the complex and screening for symptoms.
Pusieron el complejo en cuarentena.
Kowloon is the most densely populated area in the world...
Kowloon es un בrea densamente poblada...
and Hong Kong is a harbor.
...y Hong Kong es una bahםa.
It's going to spread.
Se va a esparcir.
Hong Kong is sending us blood samples.
Hong Kong nos enviarב muestras de sangre.
We're also looking at samples from London.
Tambiיn analizaremos sangre de Londres.
Two clusters: One at a hotel, the other at a health club.
Dos grupos: Uno en un hotel, otro en un centro deportivo.
Five dead, encephalitis.
Cinco muertos. Encefalitis.
And there's the man on the bus in Tokyo.
Y estב al hombre que muriף en el autobתs de Tokio.
- Three dead in that cluster. - Any of them travel to China or London?
- Tres muertos en ese grupo. - ¿Alguno viajף a China o a Londres?
We're checking.
Lo estamos averiguando.
Mr. Neal, I want you to stay with me here.
¡Seסor Neal, no se me vaya!
- I want you to open your eyes if you can. - He's breathing, right?
- Abra los ojos si puede. - ¿Estב respirando?
I couldn't wake him. I got home, I couldn't wake him.
¡Lleguי a mi casa y no lo podםa despertar!
We both woke up sick this morning.
¡Los dos nos sentםamos mal esta maסana!
Watch your head.
Cuidado con la cabeza.
Well, the sulci are obliterated. Let's look at the base.
Los surcos estבn destruidos. A ver la base.
Oh, my God.
Dios mםo.
You want me to take a sample, or...?
¿Quieres que tome una muestra o?
I want you to move away from the table.
Quiero que te alejes de la mesa.
- Should I call someone, or...? - Call everyone.
- ¿Llamo a alguien? - Llama a todo el mundo.
Well, these things happen up there from time to time.
Estas cosas pasan allב de vez en cuando.
Meningitis in a college dorm after a swim meet...
Meningitis en competencias de nataciףn...
or West Nile in some summer camp near a lake.
...o el virus del Nilo en campamentos de verano.
I was reading that last summer they had an outbreak of enterovirus encephalitis.
El verano pasado hubo un brote de encefalitis.
A hundred and three cases, mainly children.
Ciento tres casos, principalmente niסos.
Well, it's probably too cold up there for that right now.
En este momento hace mucho frםo para eso.
As of last night, there were five deaths and 32 cases.
Anoche ya eran cinco muertos y 32 casos.
There's a cluster in an elementary school.
Hay un grupo en una escuela primaria.
That's the kind of thing you have to be prepared for.
Prepבrese para eso.
It's gonna be all over the news.
Estarב en todas las noticias.
What's your single overriding communications objective?
¿Quי es lo principal que quiere comunicar?
We're isolating the sick and quarantining those who we believe were exposed.
Estamos aislando a los enfermos y a los expuestos.
Okay, good.
Muy bien.
As of this moment, you and I are attached at the cell phone.
Usted y yo estamos conectados por los celulares.
If you need resources, call me. If you get into a political dogfight, call me.
Si necesita recursos, llבmeme. Si tiene problemas polםticos, llבmeme.
If you find yourself wide awake, staring at the walls at 3 a.m...
Si se desvela y a las 3:00 a.m...
wondering why you took the job, call me.
...se pregunta por quי aceptף este empleo, llבmeme.
I sure hope you packed something warmer than that.
Ojalב traiga ropa mבs caliente.
We're looking at around zero with the windchill.
Estamos a alrededor de -18 °C de sensacion termica.
Don't want you to catch cold.
No quiero que se resfrםe.
Do you wanna go to the hotel first, get situated?
¿Quiere ir primero al hotel?
I'd prefer to get started, if that's possible.
- Prefiero empezar ya, si es posible. - Bien.
Your dad's in isolation.
Tu papב estב en aislamiento.
You can go up to the window, pick up the phone, and you can talk to him.
Puedes ir a la ventana y hablar con יl por el telיfono.
- Hey. - Dad.
- Hola. - Papב.
- Are you sick?
- ¿Estבs enfermo?
No, no, no. I'm-- Uh....
No, no, no. Estoy...
This is all just, you know, a precaution. They're, you know, just making sure.
Es una precauciףn para estar seguros.
But you were with them. You could still get it.
Pero estuviste con ellos. Podrםas enfermarte.
No, I won't. Um, they said this happens really, really fast.
No me voy a enfermar. Dicen que sucede muy rבpido.
And, uh, I'm fine. There's nothing wrong with me.
Estoy bien. No tengo nada.
We're okay. We're okay.
No tengo nada. Estamos bien. Estamos bien.
And Clark?
¿Y Clark?
Yeah, you know, I, um....
Sabes...
I wasn't there. I went, uh, in the ambulance with, uh, Beth.
Yo no estuve. Me fui en la ambulancia con Beth.
And, uh, I just didn't-- I--
Y simplemente no...
I left him with, uh, Carrie Anne.
Lo dejי con Carrie Anne.
I should have been there.
Yo deberםa haber estado ahם.
- I could have helped. - No, no, no. Honey, no, no.
- ¡Hubiera podido ayudar! - No, mi vida, no.
It's good that you weren't there. I'm happy.
Me alegro de que no estuviste.
If something had happened to you, I mean, I'd....
Si te hubiera pasado algo...
Honey, you're here now, you know. I'm happy about that.
Estבs aquם ahora. Eso me da gusto.
When are you coming home?
¿Cuבndo vuelves a casa?
Soon. Very soon. They, you know....
Pronto, muy pronto.
- Why don't you go, uh, to your mom's? - No.
- ¿Por quי no vas a casa de tu mamב? - No.
- Just stay in Wisconsin. - No. She doesn't need me.
- Quיdate en Wisconsin. - No. Ella no me necesita.
She's got Dan. I live here.
Ella tiene a Dan. Yo vivo aquם.
You don't have anybody. I'm not leaving you.
Tת no tienes a nadie. No te voy a dejar.
We have 47 cases and eight deaths as of 5 this afternoon.
Tenemos 47 casos y ocho muertos.
It's a weekend. These numbers might be low.
DEPARTAMENTO DE SALUD DE MINNESOTA
People are staying home for a couple days, see if they get better.
La gente se estב quedando en casa para mejorarse.
At this point, I think we have to believe this is respiratory.
Debe de ser algo respiratorio.
- Maybe fomites too. - What's that, fomites?
- O quizב por fףmites. - ¿Quי es eso? ¿Fףmites?
Uh, it refers to transmission from surfaces.
Se refiere a la transmisiףn por medio de superficies.
The average person touches their face 2- or 3000 times a day.
La gente se toca la cara entre 2000 y 3000 veces al dםa.
- Two- or 3000 times a day? - Three to five times every waking minute.
- ¿Entre 2000 y 3000 veces al dםa? - De tres a cinco veces por minuto.
In between, we're touching doorknobs...
Mientras, tocamos puertas...
water fountains, elevator buttons and each other.
...fuentes de agua, botones de elevadores, gente.
Those things become fomites.
Eso son fףmites.
Is this something we wanna release to the press? Respiratory and fomites?
¿Se lo vamos a decir a la prensa? ¿Respiratorio o fףmites?
- How's the public gonna react? - Hard to say. A plastic shark in a movie...
- ¿Cףmo reaccionarב el pתblico? - No se sabe. Un tiburףn de pelםcula...
will keep people from getting in the ocean, but a warning on cigarettes--
...espanta, pero un aviso en los cigarrillos...
We need to walk the governor through this before we freak everybody out.
Hay que informar al gobernador antes de espantar a todo el mundo.
I mean.... we can't even tell people right now what they should be afraid of.
No sabemos cףmo advertir a la gente.
We tried that with swine flu. All we did was get healthy people scared.
Con la influenza porcina asustamos a la gente sana.
It's the biggest shopping weekend of the year.
- Es el fin de semana de mבs compras. - Quizב deberםamos cerrar las escuelas.
And who stays home with the kids? People that work at stores.
¿Quiיn se queda con los niסos? ¿Los empleados de tiendas?
Government workers. People that work at hospitals.
¿Del gobierno? ¿De hospitales?
When will we know what this is? What causes it, what cures it?
¿Cuבndo vamos a saber la causa y la cura...
Things that keep people calm.
...para calmar a la gente?
What we need to determine is this:
Lo que necesitamos determinar es esto...
For every person who gets sick...
Cada persona que se enferma...
how many other people are they likely to infect?
...¿cuבnta gente es probable que infecte?
So for seasonal flu, that's usually about one.
Con la influenza anual normalmente es una.
Smallpox, on the other hand, it's over three.
Con viruela, sin embargo, son mבs de tres.
Now, before we had a vaccine...
Antes de que hubiera vacuna...
polio spread at a rate between four and six.
...la polio contagiaba a entre cuatro y seis personas.
Now, we call that number...
A ese nתmero le llamamos...
the R-nought.
...el nתmero Ro.
R stands for the reproductive rate of the virus.
La "R" representa la tasa de reproducciףn del virus.
Any ideas what that might be for this?
¿Saben cuבl es la tasa aquם?
How fast it multiplies depends on a variety of factors.
La velocidad para multiplicarse depende de varios factores.
The incubation period, how long a person is contagious.
El perםodo de incubaciףn, cuבnto tiempo la persona es contagiosa.
Sometimes people can be contagious without even having symptoms.
A veces la gente puede ser contagiosa sin tener sםntomas.
We need to know that too.
Tambiיn necesitamos saber eso.
We need to know how big the population of people susceptible to the virus might be.
Hay que conocer el tamaסo de la poblaciףn susceptible al virus.
So far that appears to be everyone with hands, a mouth and a nose.
Al parecer es cualquiera con manos, boca y nariz.
Once we know the R-nought, we'll be able to get a handle on the scale of the epidemic.
Una vez que conozcamos el Ro, sabremos la escala de la epidemia.
So it's an epidemic now. An epidemic of what?
O sea que es una epidemia. ¿Una epidemia de quי?
We sent samples to the CDC.
Enviamos muestras al gobierno.
In 72 hours, we'll know what it is, if we're lucky.
En 72 horas sabremos quי es, si tenemos suerte.
Clearly, we're not lucky.
Claramente, no tenemos suerte.
What do we got?
¿Quי tenemos?
A young woman in Minnesota, recently traveled to China.
Una mujer joven en Minnesota. Viajף hace poco a China.
Son also died.
El hijo tambiיn muriף.
As of this morning, 87 cases, 15 deaths.
Hasta esta maסana, 87 casos, 15 muertes.
- Did you have a good Thanksgiving? - I worked.
- ¿Tuviste un buen Dםa de Gracias? - Trabajי.
You? Really?
¿Tת? ¿De verdad?
Texas. Salmonella. Pretty limited.
Texas. Salmonelosis. Bastante limitada.
- Mine was great, thanks. - Oh.
El mםo estuvo bien, gracias.
It's pleomorphic, but tends toward ovoid in shape.
Es pleomףrfico, tendiendo a forma ovoide.
I see structures on the surface that look like glycoproteins...
Veo estructuras que parecen glicoproteםnas...
but there's nothing morphologically pathognomonic.
...pero nada patognomףnico.
We tested all her antibodies. I didn't see much cross-reactivity.
Probamos los anticuerpos. Vi pocas reacciones.
Her body had no idea what to do with it. It just kept amplifying.
Su cuerpo no sabםa quי hacer. Siguiף amplificando.
Send it to Sussman in San Francisco.
Mבndaselo a Sussman en San Francisco. Si יl no sabe, nadie sabe.
It shows novel characteristics and appears to be chimeric in origin.
Muestra caracterםsticas novedosas y parece ser de origen quimיrico.
Virus is 15 to 19 kilobases in length and containing six to 10 genes.
El virus tiene entre 15 y 19 kilobases de longitud...
Typical of a paramyxovirus.
Tםpico de un paramixovirus.
It's Godzilla, King Kong and Frankenstein all in one.
Es Godzilla, King Kong y Frankenstein juntos.
- Hold on. Shit, I'll call you back. - You've got it in there.
- Te vuelvo a llamar. - Usted lo tiene ahם, ¿no?
- Get away from here. - Where'd it come from? Military?
- Lבrgate, Alan. - ¿De dףnde saliף?
You're not a doctor and you're not a writer.
No eres doctor ni escritor.
Yes, I am a writer. Yes, I am.
Sם soy escritor. Lo soy.
Blogging is not writing. It's graffiti with punctuation.
Bloguear no es escribir. Es graffiti con puntuaciףn.
I am a journalist, and there's informed discussion on the blogosphere...
Yo soy periodista y en la blogosfera hay discusiones...
that this is a biological weapon.
...de que es un arma biolףgica.
You wanna talk to me, call my office and make an appointment.
Si quieres hablar conmigo, llama a mi oficina y haz una cita.
- Dr. Cheever? - Yes.
- ¿Doctor Cheever? - Sם.
- Do you have a moment? - Sure.
- ¿Tiene un momento? - Claro que sם.
We found him. Tell the unit on the way to his house to come in.
Lo encontrי. Llama a la unidad que va a su casa.
Excuse me. Who are you?
Disculpe. ¿Quiיn es usted?
My name is Dennis French with the Department of Homeland Security.
Dennis French, Departamento de Seguridad Nacional.
And what's this all about?
¿Y de quי se trata?
Rear Admiral Haggerty's expecting us in the emergency operations center.
El contralmirante Haggert nos espera en el Centro de Urgencias.
We can discuss it there.
Lo podemos discutir ahם.
This happened in Kowloon.
Esto pasף en Kowloon.
Today we've got workers at a casino in Macao striking over conditions.
Hoy trabajadores de un casino en Macao se pusieron en huelga.
Three have died in one bunkhouse. CIA thinks there may be a connection.
Tres murieron en un dormitorio. La CIA cree que hay una conexiףn.
Casinos are of particular concern to Homeland Security.
Los casinos le preocupan a Seguridad Nacional.
Someone's ready to blow themselves up at a pizzeria or the local market...
Si alguien estב listo para volarse en un mercado...
the thought of getting themselves sick with smallpox...
...la idea de enfermarse con la peste...
and walking through a crowded casino must have crossed their mind.
...y caminar por un casino puede ocurrםrsele.
What did they die of, the three?
¿De quי murieron los tres?
Reports are vague. Seizures, comas.
Hay reportes vagos. Convulsiones, comas.
We've reached out to the WHO, see what they know.
Ya contactamos a la OMS, a ver quי saben ellos.
If you were gonna plan it, can't think of a better time.
Un buen momento serםa el Dםa de Gracias.
- Plan what? - An attack.
- ¿Para quי? - Un ataque.
Is there any way someone could weaponize the bird flu?
¿Se puede hacer un arma con la gripe aviar?
Someone doesn't have to weaponize the bird flu.
No hay que hacer un arma.
The birds are doing that.
Las aves la estבn haciendo.
Officials are reporting the closing of Mondale Elementary School...
El gobierno reportף el cierre de una escuela...
in suburban Minneapolis...
...en Minneapolis...
in response to the recent outbreak of a still-unknown disease...
...en respuesta al brote de una enfermedad...
that has so far taken the life of a school nurse and three students.
...que matף a una enfermera y tres estudiantes.
Other schools in District 281 will remain open...
Otras escuelas en el Distrito 281 seguirבn abiertas...
but parents have been notified to keep home any children with symptoms.
...pero niסos con sםntomas no deben asistir.
The Department of Health is awaiting confirmation...
El Departamento de Salubridad espera confirmaciףn...
but sources say these new cases may be connected to the sudden death...
...pero parece que los casos estבn relacionados con la muerte...
of a 34-year-old AIMM Alderson executive...
...de una ejecutiva de 34 aסos de AIMM Alderson...
and her 6-year-old son this holiday weekend.
...y su hijo de seis aסos el fin de semana pasado.
Hello. I'm Dr. Mears.
Yo soy la doctora Mears...
I'm an Epidemic Intelligence Service officer...
...del Servicio de Inteligencia de Epidemias.
and I'm here from Atlanta to find out what happened to Beth Emhoff.
Vengo de Atlanta a averiguar quי le pasף a Beth Emhoff.
Okay, I'm gonna ask you some questions and see if--
Les voy a hacer unas preguntas para ver si...
There was a package she messengered from Hong Kong.
Beth mandף un paquete de Hong Kong.
- I opened it with scissors. I'm not sure if-- - No. It shouldn't be an issue.
- Lo abrם con tijeras. - No debe de ser problema.
Virus can't live for days on a box.
Los virus no pueden vivir en una caja.
We did Pilates together.
Hacםamos pilates juntas.
I called her after she got back. I never heard from her.
La llamי cuando volviף. Ella no me llamף.
- So you had no contact with her? - No.
- ¿No tuvo contacto con ella? - No.
- Did she go to the class? - I didn't see her there.
- ¿Ella fue a la clase? - No la vi ahם.
We had coffee the day she left.
Tomamos un cafי el dםa que se fue.
I think she might have moved my cup because it was on some papers.
Quizב moviף mi taza porque estaba sobre unos papeles.
- I can't remember. - How many days ago?
- No me acuerdo. - ¿Hace cuבntos dםas?
About 10 days.
Unos diez.
That's okay. The incubation period is less than that.
Estב bien. El perםodo de incubaciףn es menos que eso.
Is there anyone else who might have had contact with her?
¿Alguien mבs pudo haber tenido contacto con ella?
- This was everyone. - Aaron Barnes did.
- Solo nosotros. - Tambiיn Aaron Barnes.
Barnes? He worked on another floor.
Trabajaba en otro piso.
There were documents she needed. He picked her up from the airport.
Beth necesitaba firmar unos documentos. ֹl la recogiף.
He picked her up from the airport? Where is he?
- ¿La recogiף en el aeropuerto? - Sם.
Hello?
¿Diga?
- Hello? Mr. Barnes? - Hello? Yes.
- ¿Diga? ¿Seסor Barnes? - ¿Diga? Sם.
This is Dr. Mears from the Centers for Disease Control.
Habla la doctora Mears de los Centros de Control de Enfermedades.
- I believe-- - Hi.
- Creo que... - Hola.
Hi. I believe you may have had contact with Beth Emhoff last week.
Usted pudo haber tenido contacto con Beth Emhoff hace unos dםas.
Yeah, I picked her up at the airport. What's this about?
Sם, la recogם del aeropuerto. ¿De quי se trata?
- And how are you feeling today? - Uh, pretty cruddy, to be honest.
- ¿Cףmo se siente hoy? - Bastante mal.
My head is pounding. I probably picked up some bug.
Me duele la cabeza. Creo que pesquי algo.
- Where are you right now? - I'm on the bus, heading to work.
- ¿Dףnde estב? - En un autobתs, yendo al trabajo.
- I'd like you to get off immediately. - What?
- Bבjese inmediatamente. - ¿Quי?
- He's on a bus. - Where?
- Estב en un autobתs. - ¿Dףnde?
- Where? Where's the bus, Aaron? - Um.... Uh....
¿Dףnde? ¿Dףnde estב el autobתs, Aaron?
- Lake and Lyndale. What's going on? - Lake and Lyndale.
- En Lake y Lyndale. ¿Quי pasa? - En Lake y Lyndale.
I really need you to get off that bus.
Bבjese del autobתs.
It's possible you've come in contact with an infectious disease...
Es probable que haya tenido contacto con una enfermedad...
and you're highly contagious. Do you understand?
...y que sea contagioso.
I want you to get off now. And stay away from other people.
Bבjese ahora y no se acerque a nadie.
Now what do I do?
¿Y ahora quי hago?
Don't talk to anyone, don't touch anyone.
No hable con nadie, no toque a nadie. Eso es lo mבs importante.
- We'll send somebody to meet the bus. - Okay.
- Enviaremos a alguien a recogerlo. - Bien.
I'm on my way to you now, Aaron.
Voy en camino a verlo, Aaron.
What about my kids? I touched them.
¿Y mis hijos? ¡Los toquי!
It was a groundbreaking ceremony for a new factory.
Fue a la inauguraciףn de una fבbrica.
She traveled a lot for work.
Viajaba mucho por su trabajo.
Did her work involve contact with livestock in any way?
¿Su trabajo requerםa contacto con ganado?
- Did you keep any pets at home? - No.
- ¿Ustedes tenםan mascotas? - No.
No.
No.
Did she mention seeing anyone who was sick?
¿Mencionף haber visto a alguien enfermo?
Anyone on a plane?
¿A alguien en un aviףn?
No.
No.
She went through customs in Chicago at 11:15 a.m...
Pasף la aduana en Chicago a las 11:15 a.m...
and then took a flight to Minneapolis at 6 p.m.
...y luego tomף un vuelo a Minneapolis a las 6:00 p.m.
Any idea what she did in Chicago during that layover?
¿Tiene idea de quי hizo en Chicago?
Did she have meetings?
¿Tuvo reuniones?
Is there any reason she might have left the airport?
¿Pudo haber salido del aeropuerto por alguna razףn?
Why? I mean, is there someone sick in Chicago?
¿Por quי? ¿Hay alguien enfermo en Chicago?
Uh, before we were married, my wife had a relationship...
Antes de que nos casבramos, mi esposa tuvo una relaciףn...
with a man in Chicago named Jon Neal.
...con un hombre en Chicago llamado Jon Neal.
Is Jon Neal sick?
¿Estב enfermo Jon Neal?
Did we get this from him?
¿ֹl nos pegף esto?
- We're investigating all the possibilities. - No. I think I have a right to know.
- Estamos investigando. - Yo tengo derecho a saber.
Look at where I am here.
Mire dףnde estoy.
- I can't disclose that information. I'm sorry. - No, I'm just-- I'm just trying to understand.
- No puedo revelar esa informaciףn. - Solo estoy tratando de entender.
I know.
Ya lo sי.
We're getting the same results as Sussman.
Concordamos con Sussman.
We've sequenced the virus, determined its origin...
Sacamos la secuencia del virus...
and we've modeled the way it enters the cells of the lung and the brain.
...y modelamos cףmo entra en el pulmףn y el cerebro.
The virus contains both bat and pig sequences.
Hay secuencias de murciיlago y de cerdo.
The dark green is pig, and the light green is bat.
El verde oscuro es cerdo y el claro es murciיlago.
And here you can see the crossover event.
Y aquם estב el evento de recombinaciףn.
Uh, bat, bat, and pig, bat.
Murciיlago, murciיlago, cerdo y murciיlago.
And here is a model of the virus and how it attaches to its host.
Este es un modelo del virus y cףmo se adhiere a su huיsped.
The blue is virus, and the gold is human, and the red is the viral attachment protein...
El azul es virus y el dorado es humano...
and the green is its receptor in the human cells.
El verde es su receptor en cיlulas humanas.
These receptors are found in the cells of both the respiratory tract...
Estos receptores estבn en las cיlulas del aparato respiratorio...
and the central nervous system.
...y del sistema nervioso.
And the virus attaches to the cell like a key slipping into a lock.
El virus se acopla a la cיlula como una llave entra a una cerradura.
Somewhere in the world, the wrong pig met up with the wrong bat.
En algתn lado, el cerdo equivocado conociף al murciיlago equivocado.
- You ever seen anything like this before? - No. And it's still changing.
- ¿Habםas visto algo parecido? - No. Sigue cambiando.
It's figuring us out faster than we're figuring it out.
Nos descifra mבs rבpido que nosotros a יl.
It doesn't have anything else to do.
No tiene otra cosa que hacer.
So we have a novel virus with a mortality rate in the low 20s...
Tenemos un virus con una tasa de mortalidad del 20 al 25 por ciento.
no treatment protocol, and no vaccine at this time.
No hay ningתn tratamiento ni vacuna.
That is correct.
Exactamente.
From here on out, I want no one working on this except at BSL-4.
De ahora en adelante, nadie trabaja en esto mבs que BSL-4.
Last thing we need is for this to walk out of the lab on the bottom of someone's shoe.
No necesitamos que esto salga del laboratorio en un zapato.
Dr. Sussman's office.
Oficina del doctor Sussman.
Lan, hi. Ally Hextall.
Ian, hola. Ally Hextall.
We need to shut you down. This thing's too hot. Uh....
Necesitamos detener lo tuyo. Es demasiado peligroso.
- BSL-4 only at this point. - I think that's a mistake.
- Solo BSL-4 a partir de ahora. - Eso es un error.
Cook your samples. Uh, destroy everything.
Cocina tus muestras, destruye todo.
- We can't risk it. - We're making progress.
- Es mucho riesgo. - Estamos avanzando.
You limit this to government-run BSL-4s, it'll take forever.
Si limitas esto a BSL-4 del gobierno, va a tardar mucho.
I can do this.
Yo puedo hacerlo.
I'm sorry.
Lo siento.
Yeah.
Sם.
Sure, Ally.
Claro, Ally.
Can you repeat the affected cities so far?
¿Nos repite las ciudades afectadas?
Again, the affected cities are...
Las ciudades afectadas son...
Minneapolis, Chicago, Los Angeles, Boston and Salt Lake.
DֽA 8
We expect that list to grow...
Esperamos que la lista crezca...
as people return home from their holidays.
...cuando la gente vuelva de vacaciones.
Yes?
¿Sם?
Dr. Cheever, how many people are infected...
¿Cuבnta gente se ha infectado y cuבnta gente ha muerto?
and how many have died?
BIOTERRORISMO - JIHAD YEMEN ELLIS CHEEVER
so any figure I give you is likely to be low.
...asם que cualquier cifra serםa baja.
We're still calculating the mortality rate at this time.
Estamos calculando la tasa de mortalidad.
Uh, Dr. Cheever, are you concerned...
¿Le preocupa que los Centros de Control tengan un problema de credibilidad...
after the perceived overreaction to H1N1?
...despuיs de la reacciףn excesiva al H1N1?
I'd rather the story be that we overreacted...
Prefiero que la noticia sea que exageramos...
than that many people lost their lives because we didn't do enough.
...a que muchos murieron por no tomar medidas.
That's why we're here.
Por ello estamos aquם.
It's also why the World Health Organization is sending an epidemiologist to Hong Kong.
Por eso la Organizaciףn de la Salud mandף a alguien a Hong Kong.
Hard to know what it is without where it came from.
Es difםcil saber quי es sin saber de dףnde vino.
Our first job with these things is to find ground zero.
Necesitamos encontrar el punto de origen...
Figure out how it jumped into the population.
...averiguar cףmo saltף a la poblaciףn.
We do know that a patient in Minnesota...
Sabemos que una paciente de Minnesota...
traveled to that part of the world.
...viajף a esa parte del mundo.
We believe that there are approximately 89,000 cases at this point...
Creemos que hay aproximadamente 89000 casos en este momento.
and that we are heading toward 267,000.
Y que vamos camino a 267000.
And from there, using our model, based on an R-nought of two...
A partir de ahם, usando nuestro modelo basado en un Ro de dos...
here is where we expect to be in 48 hours.
...esperamos estar aquם en 48 horas.
Dr. Cheever, perhaps you can update us on the research.
Doctor Cheever, pףnganos al corriente de la investigaciףn.
As of right now, no one has found a good way to grow the virus in cells.
Nadie ha encontrado la manera de cultivar el virus en cיlulas.
Why is that?
¿A quי se debe eso?
Because it kills every cell we put it in. A pig, a chicken, everything.
Mata todas las cיlulas en que lo ponemos, de cerdo, de pollo.
Until we can grow it, and a great deal of it, we can't experiment with it.
Sino lo cultivamos en cantidades, no podemos experimentar con יl...
And until then, we can't vaccinate against it.
...y no podemos desarrollar la vacuna.
Have you found any treatment at all? Any antivirus? Anything?
¿Han encontrado algתn tratamiento? ¿Un antivirus? ¿Algo?
No.
No.
Beth Emhoff used an ATM at a casino in Macao.
Beth Emhoff usף el cajero automבtico de un casino en Macao.
Citibank released her records.
Citibank nos dio sus datos.
We have her using the machine at 10:43 just off the casino floor.
Sabemos que usף la mבquina a las 10:43, junto a las mesas de juego.
I wanna see the casino security footage for two hours on either side of that.
Quiero ver los videos de las cבmaras dos horas antes y despuיs.
Is there a problem?
¿Hay algתn problema?
Oh, they're from my village. They found a new cluster there.
Son de mi pueblo. Encontraron un nuevo grupo ahם.
- Is your family still there? - My mother has symptoms.
- ¿Tu familia sigue ahם? - Mi madre tiene sםntomas.
I'll get you the footage you require. Excuse me.
Le voy a conseguir lo que quiere. Disculpe.
Dr. Sussman, I heard that they were shutting us down.
Doctor Sussman, me enterי que van a detener nuestra investigaciףn.
Yeah, I just have to deal with the samples.
Solo tengo que lidiar con las muestras.
If it's just a matter of destroying them, I can do it.
Si hay que destruirlas, yo puedo hacerlo.
No, I'll take care of it. You go on home.
Yo me encargo. Vete a casa.
I'll do that, and then I just want to recheck some data.
Quiero revisar unos datos.
He grew it.
Lo cultivף.
He tried antibodies and immunological MAC outlines...
Probף con anticuerpos y con MAC como nosotros.
but the key was a fetal-bat cell line from Geelong.
La clave fue ADN fetal...
- We didn't have it. - He grew it in a BSL-3.
...que no tenםamos. - Lo cultivף en un BSL-3.
Ally, what the hell was he doing working with it in a BSL-3?
¿Cףmo diablos trabajף en un BSL-3?
Ignoring me.
Me ignorף.
He's gonna publish. Shit. What does he want?
Lo va a publicar. ¡Demonios! ¿Quי quiere?
A box of cigars. He had a choice, Ellis.
Una caja de habanos. Tenםa opciones.
He could have gone into business for himself.
Podםa haberlo vendido.
There's no doubt he was approached, but he gave it to us.
Seguro que tuvo ofertas, pero nos lo dio a nosotros.
- And we're supposed to trust him? - We don't have a choice.
- ¿Debemos confiar en יl? - No tenemos mבs remedio.
The Centers for Disease Control and Prevention in the United States...
Los Centros de Control de Enfermedades...
and the World Health Organization in Switzerland...
DֽA 12
confirmed today that Dr. Lan Sussman of San Francisco...
...confirmaron que el doctor Ian Sussman de San Francisco...
has succeeded in growing the MEV-1 virus in a laboratory setting.
...logrף cultivar el virus MEv-1 en un laboratorio.
Officials at the CDC cautioned that the breakthrough is only the first step...
Los representantes advirtieron que este avance es solo el primer paso...
toward developing a vaccine...
...para desarrollar una vacuna...
which is likely still months away from human trials.
...que estב a meses de pruebas en humanos.
The WHO estimates the number of people infected worldwide to be over 8 million.
La OMS calcula que el nתmero de infectados rebasa los ocho millones.
Now it all changes.
Ahora todo cambia.
Sussman gets anointed by the National Academy of Sciences...
La Academia Nacional de Ciencias unge a Sussman...
and every pharmaceutical executive gets a hard-on.
...y los ejecutivos farmacיuticos se excitan.
They'll be growing the virus in every lab on Earth.
Van a cultivar el virus en todos los laboratorios.
It's a bad day to be a rhesus monkey.
Pobres de los monos.
Crikey, first we shoot them into space, now we'll be shooting them full of virus.
Primero los lanzamos al espacio y ahora les metemos virus.
So this is where we need your expertise.
Necesitamos su asesorםa.
Pharmaceutical stocks are already through the roof.
Las acciones de farmacיuticos ya se dispararon.
What's next? Where's the opportunity?
¿Pero quי sigue? ¿Dףnde estב la oportunidad?
Now, you saw that Shinko bus thing day one.
Usted vio lo del autobתs el primer dםa.
That's why we wanted this meeting.
Por eso querםamos esta reuniףn.
When I turned on my computer this morning...
Cuando prendם mi computadora hoy...
I had over 2 million unique visitors, all looking for the truth.
...mבs de dos millones de visitantes querםan la verdad.
You think they wanna see me talking to some hedge-fund guy?
¿Cree que quieren que hable con un inversionista?
Mr. Krumwiede, we don't invent need here.
Nosotros no inventamos la necesidad.
We just analyze it, predict it.
Solo la analizamos, la predecimos.
You tell me what it costs to look into your crystal ball.
Dםgame cuבnto cuesta ver en su bola de cristal.
You're familiar with forsythia?
¿Conoce la forsitia?
- No, I'm not. - What I'm about to tell you is backed up...
- No, no la conozco. - Esto estב respaldado...
by testimonials that will appear shortly in the media.
...por testimonios que aparecerבn pronto en los medios.
I'll be talking about it extensively in the days ahead.
Yo hablarי mucho de ella.
What does forsythia do?
¿Quי hace la forsitia?
It's the cure.
Es la cura.
If I'm immune, can't you use my blood to cure this?
Si yo soy inmune, ¿no puede usar mi sangre para curarlo?
Blood serums can take a long time to make, and are very expensive.
Hacer un suero tarda mucho y es muy caro.
But the good news here is that you're not going to get sick.
Lo bueno es que usted no se va a enfermar.
Okay. Um....
Bien.
Then that would mean that my daughter can't get it either, right?
Eso significa que mi hija tampoco se puede enfermar, ¿verdad?
I can't promise you that.
No le puedo prometer eso.
But isn't that something that she would inherit from me?
¿No es algo que ella heredף de mם?
Well, half her immune system came from you...
La mitad de su sistema inmunolףgico vino de usted...
but the other half came from her mother.
...y la otra vino de su madre.
--almost three hours.
¡Son casi tres horas!
I need to see a doctor or a supervisor or something.
Necesito ver a un doctor o a un supervisor.
I wanna know if he has this thing on the news.
¡Quiero saber si tiene lo de las noticias!
I'm sorry, sir, we're doing the best we can.
Disculpe, estamos haciendo todo lo posible.
Can I just speak to an administrator or something? Anybody.
¿Puedo hablar con un administrador?
Sir, please be patient. We'll get you in--
- Tenga paciencia. Va a entrar. - ¡Estב enfermo!
My wife makes me take off my clothes in the garage.
Mi esposa me hace desvestirme en el garaje.
Then she leaves out a bucket of warm water and some soap.
Me deja una cubeta de agua tibia y jabףn.
And then she douses everything in hand sanitizer after I leave.
Empapa todo con lociףn antibacteriana cuando me voy.
I mean, she's overreacting, right?
Estב exagerando, ¿no?
Not really. And stop touching your face, Dave.
La verdad, no. Y deja de tocarte la cara, Dave.
Okay, we'll put the air lock here.
Pondremos el compartimiento aquם.
I want 25 rows of 10 beds apiece. The most febrile cases at this end.
Quiero 25 filas de diez camas. Los casos mבs febriles ahם.
We'll set up triage outside, FEMA can handle food in the basement...
Los clasificaremos afuera, FEMA se encargarב de comida en el sףtano...
and we'll need to be operational within the next 24 to 48 hours.
...y necesitamos estar listos en las prףximas 24 a 48 horas.
Gotcha.
Entiendo.
- Nice job, Dave. This will work. - Thanks.
- Bien hecho, Dave. Esto servirב. - Gracias.
Now find me three more just like it.
Bתscame tres mבs iguales.
Excuse me, Dr. Mears. Is this coming out of your budget or ours?
Disculpe, Dra. Mears. ¿Esto sale de su presupuesto o del nuestro?
WHO has confirmed that the Hong Kong sample...
La OMS ha confirmado que las muestras de Hong Kong...
matches London, Tokyo and Abu Dhabi...
...Londres, Tokio y Abu Dhabi...
and we're seeing large clusters in from Frankfurt and Cairo.
...son iguales y tenemos grupos grandes en Frankfurt y El Cairo.
Are we any closer to an index patient?
¿Estamos cerca de un paciente םndice?
Could be your Beth Emhoff or the guy on the bus in Japan.
Puede ser su Beth Emhoff o el tipo del autobתs en Japףn.
Someone else who crawled off the grid. How you doing?
O alguien mבs del que no hay rastro. ¿Cףmo estב usted?
Yeah, good. I'm going into a meeting with--
Bien. Voy a una junta...
No, I didn't ask what you were doing, I asked how you were doing.
No le preguntי quי hacםa, sino cףmo estaba.
How are you doing?
¿Cףmo estב?
I'm, uh....
Estoy...
I'm fine.
Estoy bien.
Fine?
¿Bien?
You know, I was in the field for 15 years.
Estuve 15 aסos en el campo...
I've seen a lot of shit. If you're not doing fine, you can tell me.
...y he visto muchas cosas. Si no estב bien me lo puede decir.
You ever have to tell a man who just lost his wife and stepson...
¿Le ha dicho a un hombre que reciיn perdiף a su mujer...
that his wife was cheating on him before she died?
...que su esposa lo estaba engaסando?
No, I haven't.
Eso no me ha tocado.
I'm sure you did the best you could.
Seguro hizo lo que pudo.
You gotta try to remember to sleep once in a while.
Acuיrdese de dormir a veces.
When was the last time you had something that didn't come out of a vending machine?
¿Cuבndo fue la תltima vez que comiף algo que no fuera de mבquina?
Taco Bell.
¿Taco Bell?
Local officials are now saying over 3000 cases have been confirmed...
Oficiales locales dicen que 3000 casos han sido confirmados...
in the western suburbs...
...en los suburbios occidentales...
as well as the first cases reported in Ramsey, Carlton and Saint Louis counties...
...y hay casos nuevos en Ramsey, Carlton y Saint Louis.
as the virus continues to spread.
- El virus sigue esparciיndose. - ¡Lo tengo!
- Got it! - A state Health Department spokesperson...
Un vocero de Salubridad Estatal...
at this hour is appealing to hospitals as far away as lowa for medicine.
...estב pidiendo medicina de hospitales en Iowa.
No, don't open that door. Don't open the door.
¡No, no abras esa puerta! ¡No la abras!
- It's Andrew. - Uh, sorry, Andrew, I can't let you in.
- ¡Es Andrew! - Disculpa, Andrew. No puedes entrar.
I just came to give my condolences, Mr. Emhoff.
Solo vine a darle el pיsame, seסor Emhoff.
I understand. Thank you. Uh, but I can't let you in.
Entiendo. Gracias, pero no puedes entrar.
I'll just leave them, then.
Entonces las dejarי aquם.
No, actually, you should take them. Uh, thank you, though.
No, llיvatelas, pero gracias de todos modos.
- I'll call you later. - Bye.
- ¡Te llamo luego! - Adiףs.
We just, you know, aren't gonna take any chances.
No nos podemos arriesgar.
- Do you know how to play this? - No, I have no idea what's going on.
- ¿Sabe jugar este? - No tengo idea de quי estב pasando.
But it looks fun.
Parece divertido.
You wanna try?
¿Quiere probar?
Okay.
Bien.
We'll see.
Ya veremos.
Hello. Hi.
Hola.
Oh, yeah, my turn, okay.
Sם, me toca a mם.
This one. Crab. Okay.
Este. El cangrejo.
- Hey. - Oh!
Oye.
Oh, my God. I'll do-- What is that? Which one is this?
¡Dios mםo!
- Coin. - It's a coin.
- Moneda. - Es una moneda.
Oh, okay, okay, okay.
Bien. Muy bien.
It's transmission. So we just need to know which direction.
Es transmisiףn. Necesitamos saber en quי direcciףn.
But we don't know where it comes from.
Pero no sabemos de dףnde viene.
I would like to suggest that the virus started before Macao...
Quisiera sugerir que el virus empezף antes de Macao.
and maybe here in Hong Kong.
Y quizב aquם, en Hong Kong.
You're considering pronouncements with serious implications.
Estב considerando declaraciones con implicaciones serias.
A virus is too small to be seen on video camera.
Un virus es demasiado chico para ser visto con una cבmara de video.
Please, God.
Por favor, Dios.
No, no, no.
No, no. No.
Hello?
¿Diga?
This is Dr. Erin Mears in Room 821.
Habla la doctora Erin Mears del cuarto 821.
I need you to get me the names of everyone who serviced this room in the last 24 hours.
Necesito los nombres de toda la gente que limpiף este cuarto.
Also, you need to get in touch with the waiter...
Tambiיn necesita comunicarse con el camarero...
who brought me my room service last night.
...que me trajo comida anoche.
I need all of their numbers. Home, cell, everything, yes.
Necesito todos sus telיfonos, de sus casas y sus celulares.
Mears?
¿Mears?
Dr. Cheever...
Doctor Cheever...
I think I'm sick.
...creo que estoy enferma.
What? What's going on? What kind of symptoms do you have?
¿Quי pasa? ¿Quי clase de sםntomas tiene?
Can't swallow. Severe headache.
No puedo tragar. Me duele mucho la cabeza.
What's your temperature?
¿Quי temperatura tiene?
- 101.8. - Uh, listen, you can't-- You just--
- 38,8. - Escuche. No puede...
- You can't panic now, okay? - I know.
- No deje que le entre el pבnico. - Lo sי.
- Are you alone? - I've definitely infected other people.
- ¿Estב sola? - Seguro infectי a mבs gente.
You don't know that.
No puede estar segura.
- So, what should I do? - Well, I want you to stay in your room.
- ¿Quי hago? - Quיdese en su cuarto.
I'll call the Health Department, tell them you're there.
Llamarי al gobierno y les dirי que estב ahם.
- Erin, just-- You're gonna be okay. - No, I know. I know.
- Erin, te vas a poner bien. - No, ya lo sי.
- Okay. - You gotta send somebody else.
- Bien. - Necesita mandar a alguien mבs.
Yes, but you don't worry about that right now, okay?
Sם, pero no te preocupes por eso.
- Hey, I'm-- - You take care of yourself.
Tת cuםdate.
I'm sorry I couldn't finish.
Disculpe que no pude acabar.
That's-- Never mind that. Let me see what I can do about getting you back here.
Eso... Olvida eso. A ver quי puedo hacer para traerte aquם.
- I'm gonna get you home if I can, healthy. - Thank you.
- Te voy a traer. Sana. - Gracias.
- Now, you hang in there. - Bye.
- Resiste. - Adiףs.
The problem is, we just can't take delivery of the bodies.
El problema es que no podemos aceptar los cuerpos.
We have insurance issues with our own employees...
Hay problemas con el seguro, con los empleados...
with our union, not to mention the health of the mourners, to consider.
...con el sindicato y estב la salud de los afligidos.
I just-- I wanna bury my wife and my stepson...
Quiero enterrar a mi esposa y a mi hijastro...
and have a service where our friends and our family can come...
...y tener un servicio en el que todos...
and pay their respects and grieve.
...puedan presentar sus respetos.
I understand, and I am truly sorry about your loss.
Entiendo, y lamento sinceramente su pיrdida.
Have you considered other options?
¿Ha considerado otras opciones?
How can they do that? We have a family plot here.
¿Cףmo pueden hacer eso? Tenemos una desgracia familiar.
They want us to think about cremation.
Propusieron cremarlos.
They just say that it's the safest thing in a situation like this.
Dicen que es lo mבs seguro en este tipo de situaciones.
I wanna be buried with my daughter and grandson...
Yo quiero que me entierren con mi hija y mi nieto, con...
with Jack and my parents.
...Jack y mis padres.
I want us all together.
Que estemos todos juntos.
They're not gonna take them, Sarah. They're not gonna take the bodies.
No los van a aceptar. No van a aceptar los cadבveres.
I'll figure something out.
Se me ocurrirב algo. Algo se me ocurrirב.
She made mistakes, Mitch...
Ella cometiף errores, Mitch...
but I know she loved you very much.
...pero yo sי que te querםa mucho.
I'm gonna use some of these to get us some drinks, okay?
Voy a usar unas de estas para comprar bebidas. ¿Estב bien?
You have not reached Jon Neal...
No habla con Jon Neal. Pero hablarב con יl si deja un mensaje.
Hi. It's me. Um....
Hola. Soy yo.
I checked the flights, and I can actually get an earlier flight...
Estuve viendo los vuelos y puedo conseguir un vuelo mבs temprano...
that would give me a five-hour layover in Chicago...
...que me dי una escala de cinco horas en Chicago...
so let me know if that's something that you'd like me to do.
...asם que dime si quieres que lo haga.
- That's for you, okay? - Oh, thank you.
- Esto es para usted. - Muchas gracias.
Thank you very much. Thank you.
Gracias. Gracias.
- Excuse me. - Oh, my God.
Perdףn.
Thank--
Gracias.
- Emhoff gave it to the Ukrainian. - That just shows contact.
- Emhoff contagiף a la ucraniana. - Eso solo muestra contacto.
Maybe it went the other way. What about Li Fai?
Quizב fue al revיs. ¿Quי tal Li Fai?
- He was on the casino floor. - Watch this.
- Estaba en el casino. - Mira esto.
Whoa. Oh, good. Okay, come on. Let's get one together. Ready?
Que nos tomen una juntos. ¿Listo?
Cheers.
- ¡Salud!
Let's go.
Vבmonos.
That's him with Emhoff at 12:08.
Ese es, con Emhoff. A las 12:08.
I can show you the Ukrainian woman on the security camera in the elevator...
Te puedo enseסar a la ucraniana en el ascensor...
going back to her room 20 minutes earlier.
...yendo a su cuarto, 20 minutos antes.
She was gone before Li Fai started work.
Se fue antes de que Li Fai empezara a trabajar.
It came from here.
Saliף de aquם.
Emhoff is the index patient.
Emhoff es la paciente םndice.
We need to know everywhere she went before the casino.
Necesitamos saber adףnde fue antes.
I want to see her itinerary again.
Quiero ver su itinerario de nuevo.
They say the French and Americans have a cure.
Dicen que los franceses y estadounidenses tienen una cura.
They're manufacturing it in secret.
Que la fabrican en secreto.
WHO knows, but they're in bed with the Americans.
La OMS lo sabe, pero apoya a los estadounidenses.
- Who says? - The Internet.
- ¿Quiיn dice? - En Internet.
- The Internet? And you believe it? - I don't know.
- ¿En internet? ¿Y tת les crees? - No sי.
How's your mother?
¿Cףmo estב tu madre?
We tried forsythia, but she wasn't strong.
Probamos con forsitia, pero estaba muy dיbil.
There's a mass grave in Lan Tau.
Hay una fosa comתn en Lantau.
I'm sorry.
Lo siento mucho.
I'm taking this to the ministry. We need to send this to Geneva.
Voy a llevar esto al ministerio. Manda esto a Ginebra.
I need you to come with me.
Necesito que venga conmigo.
- What are you doing? - Please.
- ¿Quי haces? - Por favor.
No.
No.
What's going on? Sun Feng. What's going on? What are you doing?
¿Quי pasa? ¡Sun Feng! ¿Quי pasa? ¿Quי haces?
- What are you doing? - I'm sorry.
- ¿Quי estבs haciendo? - Perdףneme.
We couldn't wait any longer.
No podםamos esperar mבs.
While they cure each other, we're here...
Mientras ellos se curan, nosotros estamos aquם...
at the end of the line.
...al final de la lםnea.
This is what is left of my village.
Esto es lo que queda de mi pueblo.
- Are they sick? - Not yet.
- ¿Estבn enfermos? - Todavםa no.
And we're gonna keep it that way.
Y vamos a evitar que se enfermen.
You'll stay here with us until they find a cure.
Usted se va a quedar aquם hasta que haya una cura.
How is that gonna help?
¿Cףmo les va a ayudar eso?
You're gonna get us to the front of the line.
Nos van a pasar al frente de la lםnea.
Dr. Mears.
Doctora Mears.
We're just having a hard time with the logistics of evacuating you.
Tenemos dificultad con la logםstica para evacuarla...
Finding a plane and all.
...encontrar un aviףn y eso.
I got your phone.
Tengo su telיfono.
Dr. Cheever, he asked you to call if you feel up to it.
El doctor Cheever quiere que lo llame, si puede.
Now, we're setting up a special ward...
Va a haber un pabellףn...
for medical personnel and first responders at the university.
...para personal mיdico y gente de urgencias.
I wanna move you there...
Quiero llevarla ahם...
but the nurses' union is calling a work stoppage...
...pero el sindicato de enfermeras anunciף un paro laboral...
until protocols are in place.
...hasta que haya protocolos.
There are volunteers, but it's just....
Hay voluntarios, pero solo es...
It's hard right now to know where's the right place.
Es difםcil saber cuבl es el lugar correcto.
You're asking me to spend a lot of resources on one person...
Quiere que use muchos recursos en una persona...
and right now, I can't do that.
...y no puedo.
Dr. Mears would agree with me.
La doctora Mears estarםa de acuerdo.
She's one of our own, Lyle. We sent her up there.
Es de los nuestros, Lyle. Nosotros la enviamos allב.
Okay, I sent her up there. I would like to go get her back.
Yo la enviי. Quisiera sacarla.
We have a plane with an isolation pod...
Para eso hay un aviףn con cבmara aislante...
to bring our people in the field home when they're sick, right?
...para poder traer a nuestra gente si se enferma.
What's going on, Lyle?
¿Quי pasa, Lyle?
There's a sick congressman from Illinois in D.C.
Hay un congresista enfermo en Washington.
He was in Chicago over the holiday.
Pasף los dםas feriados en Chicago.
They're using the pod to fly him home.
Lo van a transportar...
Then they're closing down Midway and O'Hare.
...y luego van a cerrar los aeropuertos de Chicago.
The governor is calling the National Guard. They're setting up roadblocks.
Movilizaron a la Guardia Nacional, bloquearon caminos.
They're shutting down trade, public transportation.
Cerraron el intercambio comercial, el transporte pתblico.
The Teamsters are pulling drivers off the road.
Hasta los camioneros van a parar.
- People are still gonna slip through. - Yes, they will.
- Alguna gente se va a colar. - Sם.
The Secret Service is moving the president underground.
El Servicio Secreto pasף al presidente bajo tierra.
Congress is figuring out how to work online.
El congreso estב averiguando cףmo trabajar en lםnea.
When the word goes out...
Cuando se sepa...
there will be a run on the banks, gas stations, grocery stores, you name it.
...la gente va a vaciar los bancos...
People will panic. The virus will be the least of our worries.
Va a haber pבnico. El virus va a ser lo de menos.
It will tip over now.
Serב un caos.
We just need to make sure that nobody knows until everybody knows.
Hay que asegurarnos de que nadie sepa hasta que todos sepan.
My temperature's 101.
Mi temperatura es de 38,3.
Higher than it was earlier.
Mבs alta de lo que estaba antes.
My head hurts...
Me duele la cabeza.
and my throat feels like it's closing.
Se me estב cerrando la garganta.
This is forsythia.
Esto es forsitia.
I've been taking it since the onset of the symptoms.
La he estado tomando desde el inicio de los sםntomas.
If I'm here tomorrow, you'll know it works.
Si estoy aquם maסana, sabrבn que funciona.
Truth Serum Now. I'm Alan Krumwiede.
Esto es El Suero de la Verdad. Yo soy Alan Krumwiede.
How many people are gonna die?
¿Cuבnta gente va a morir?
Well, in 1918...
Pues en 1918...
1 percent of the population died from Spanish flu.
...el uno por ciento de la poblaciףn muriף de la gripe espaסola.
It was novel, like this, no one had ever seen it before.
Era un virus nuevo, como este. Nadie lo habםa visto antes.
- One percent of America? - One percent of the world.
- ¿El uno por ciento de Estados Unidos? - El uno por ciento del mundo.
As many as 70 million people could die, baby, maybe more.
Hasta 70 millones de personas pueden morir.
- So, what do we do? - I don't know. We try to figure it out.
- ¿Quי hacemos? - Tratamos de resolverlo.
This is why I sent Mears up there, to Minnesota.
Por eso mandי a Mears a Minnesota.
And now I can't get her back.
No la puedo traer.
She's sick, Aubrey, and I can't do anything for her...
Estב enferma y no la puedo ayudar...
because there are no nurses.
...porque no hay enfermeras.
- Why not? - Because they're on strike.
- ¿Por quי? - Porque estבn en huelga.
- How can they do that? - Because there's nothing they can do.
- ¿Cףmo pueden hacer eso? - Se sienten impotentes.
We're putting healthy people next to sick people...
Mandamos gente sana con gente enferma...
and hoping the healthy people don't get sick.
...esperando que siga sana.
- I'm sorry, Ellis, but that's not your fault. - I sent her up there, Aubrey.
- Lo siento, pero no es tu culpa. - Yo la mandי allב, Aubrey.
If one in four are dying, that means three out of four are living, right?
Si uno de cuatro muere, tres de cuatro viven, ¿no?
So the odds are in her favor.
Tiene buenas probabilidades.
I want you to get in your car and drive down here to Atlanta now.
Quiero que te subas en tu auto y que vengas a Atlanta.
You hear me, Aubrey?
¿Me oyes, Aubrey?
What are you talking about?
¿De quי hablas?
I want you to get in your car and leave Chicago.
Sתbete en tu auto y sal de Chicago.
I want you to drive here to Atlanta. Drive by yourself.
Ven manejando a Atlanta. Ven tת sola.
You do it. You do it now. Don't tell anyone and don't stop.
Hazlo ahora mismo. No le digas a nadie y no pares.
Stay away from other people, understand? Keep your distance from other people.
Y no te acerques a nadie. Mantיn tu distancia.
Call me when you're on the road, Aubrey.
Llבmame cuando estיs de camino.
Roger.
Roger.
Did you hear...?
¿Oםste?
I got people too, Dr. Cheever.
Yo tambiיn tengo gente, doctor Cheever.
We all do.
Todos la tenemos.
Hello?
¿Diga?
Hey, friend, what's up with blowing off dinner?
¿Cףmo me dejaste plantada para cenar?
- I'm sorry, Liz. - Why you so flaky? You feeling okay?
- Perdףname, Liz. - ¿Por quי eres tan irresponsable?
This flu sh--
Esto de la gripe...
Stuff is really spooky. What does Ellis say?
...es bastante aterrador. ¿Quי dice Ellis?
He says it's-- He says it's serious.
Dice... dice que es serio.
What do you mean, serious?
¿Cףmo que serio?
Where are you?
¿Dףnde estבs?
- I'm getting out of town. - What?
- Me voy de la ciudad. - ¿Quי?
I'm gonna tell you something...
Te voy a decir algo...
and you're not gonna repeat it.
...y no lo vas a repetir.
- Cover your mouth, please. - Fuck off, lady.
- Tבpese la boca, por favor. - Vבyase al demonio.
We will only be able to give out 50 doses today.
Solo podemos dar 50 dosis hoy.
- What? - That's our allotment.
- ¿Quי? - Es la asignaciףn que tenemos.
This is bullshit.
Quי tonterםa.
Hey. There-- Excuse me, there's a line here. Excuse me!
¡Disculpe! ¡Hay una cola! ¡Disculpe!
Jesus.
Dios santo.
Where's the fire department?
¿Dףnde estבn los bomberos?
Is anyone even working here?
¿Nadie estב trabajando aquם?
Just get the cereal.
Busca el cereal.
- Jory, don't touch anything. - Help me.
- Jory, no toques nada. - ¡Ayתdeme!
Okay, take your gloves off.
Quםtate los guantes.
Here, give me your hands.
Dame tus manos.
Okay. I want you to really rub this in.
Frףtalas bien.
Okay, okay, come on.
Vבmonos.
Come on, come on.
Vamos.
Hey, get away from there. Get away.
¡Alיjense de ahם! ¡Alיjense!
Lock the door.
Cierra la puerta.
Get back in your car, sir. Get back in your car.
¡Sתbase a su auto, seסor!
- No, no, I'm not-- I'm immune. - Stay back.
- ¡No, yo soy inmune! - Apבrtese.
I've already had it.
¡Ya tuve la enfermedad!
- And my daughter's not sick. - She's sick?
- ¡Y mi hija no estב enferma! - ¿Estב enferma?
She's not, no. We're just trying to get to Wisconsin.
¡No! ¡Solo queremos llegar a Wisconsin!
The border is sealed. The governor has declared a quarantine.
La frontera estב cerrada. Estamos en cuarenta.
Get back in your car.
Regrese al auto.
No, we don't wanna go back there. We wanna go across.
¡No queremos regresar! ¡Queremos cruzar!
- There is no way across. Get in your car. - We're not sick.
- No puede. Sתbase a su auto. - ¡No estamos enfermos!
Get back in your car or I will detain you.
Sino se sube a su auto, lo detengo.
Where?
¿Dףnde?
Get in the car!
¡Sתbase al auto!
- What happened? - We have to go home.
- ¿Quי pasף? - Tenemos que volver a casa.
What are you doing here?
¿Quי haces aquם?
I think I had a seizure.
Creo que sufrם una convulsiףn.
I can't-- I can't find any in the stores. I tried.
No puedo conseguirla en las tiendas. Ya tratי.
Look, I don't have any here. People broke in.
No tengo nada aquם. Me la robaron.
I'm-- I'm pregnant, Alan.
Estoy embarazada, Alan.
And I have-- I have money.
Tengo... tengo... dinero.
I can give you some money.
Te puedo dar dinero.
Lorraine, you shouldn't be out.
Lorraine, no deberםas estar afuera.
- Please, Alan. - Go home.
- Por favor, Alan. - Vete a tu casa.
I'll bring it to you when I get it.
Te la llevarי cuando la consiga.
I was wondering if I could get another blanket.
Querםa saber si me podrםa dar otra manta.
This one's very damp now.
La que tengo estב hתmeda.
I'm truly sorry, sir. We're out of blankets.
Lo lamento, ya no tenemos mantas.
We're hoping for more to be donated. We put the word out.
Esperamos que nos donen mבs. Ya corrimos la voz.
What about the heat? Can we turn that up?
¿Y la calefacciףn? ¿La podrםan prender?
I'll find out.
Voy a preguntar.
- When did we run out of body bags? - Two days ago.
¿Cuבndo se acabaron las bolsas para cadבveres?
We're trying to get more in from Canada, but they just wanna wait and see.
Pedimos mבs de Canadב, pero quieren esperar a ver.
No more lies! No more lies! No more lies!
¡Basta de mentiras!
There are stories on the Internet that in India and elsewhere...
Circulan historias por Internet de que en la India...
the drug ribavirin has been shown to be effective against this virus.
...la droga Ribavirin ha sido efectiva contra este virus.
Yet Homeland Security is telling the CDC not to make any announcements...
Pero Seguridad Nacional dijo que no lo anuncien...
until stockpiles of the drug could be secured.
...hasta no tener bastante cantidad.
Well, Dr. Gupta, there continue to be evaluations of several drugs.
Doctor Gupta, seguimos evaluando varias drogas.
Ribavirin is among them.
El Ribavirin entre ellas.
But right now, our best defense has been social distancing.
Pero nuestra mejor defensa ahora es el distanciamiento social.
No hand-shaking, staying home when you're sick...
No dar la mano, no salir si estב enfermo...
washing your hands frequently.
...lavarse mucho las manos.
Can you tell us, to date, how many people have died from this virus?
¿Nos puede decir cuבnta gente ha muerto por este virus?
Very difficult. We're still working on, uh, confirming that number.
Es muy difםcil.
There are 50 different states in this country...
Hay 50 estados en el paםs...
which means there are 50 different Health Departments...
...o sea que hay diferentes Departamentos de Salubridad...
followed by 50 different protocols.
...que siguen 50 protocolos diferentes.
Let me bring Alan Krumwiede into this debate as well.
Dיjeme incluir a Alan Krumwiede.
Uh, Alan's a freelance journalist.
Alan es un periodista.
Uh, he was the first to track the "Shinko Bus Man" video.
ֹl rastreף el video del hombre en el autobתs.
Uh, Alan, today on Twitter...
Hoy en Twitter escribiste...
you wrote that the truth about this virus is being kept from the world...
...que estבn ocultando la verdad sobre el virus...
by the CDC, by the World Health Organization...
...los Centros de Control, la OMS...
to allow friends of the administration to benefit from it...
...para permitir a amigos de la administraciףn beneficiarse...
both financially and physically.
...financiera y fםsicamente.
Uh, there are therapies we know are effective right now, like forsythia...
Hay terapias que sabemos que son efectivas, como la forsitia...
and they don't even appear on the CDC website.
...que ni aparecen en el sitio web de los Centros.
On your blog, you also wrote...
En tu blog tambiיn escribes...
that the World Health Organization is in bed with pharmaceutical companies?
...que la OMS estב aliada con las compaסםas farmacיuticas.
Because they are.
Es cierto.
That's who stands to gain from this. They're working hand in glove.
Ellos se van a beneficiar. Son como uסa y carne.
And the hand is reaching into our pockets.
Y nos quieren sacar dinero.
The CDC is exploring forsythia and other homeopathic treatments.
Los Centros estבn explorando forsitia y otros tratamientos.
But right now, there's no science to back any of these claims.
Pero no hay estudios que respalden esas declaraciones.
Or no way Dr. Cheever or the people who put him into power can profit from it.
Y no hay manera de que el doctor Cheever o la gente que lo nombrף se beneficie.
We're not ruling anything out.
No estamos descartando nada.
There are people who are sick, people who are dying, and we are doing--
Hay gente enferma, muriיndose...
They're not keeping us safe from this any more than--
No nos estבn protegiendo de esto.
We're concerned about every American citizen.
Nos preocupa la salud de todos los estadounidenses.
Dr. Cheever is being a bit disingenuous when he says "every American citizen."
El doctor Cheever estב siendo un poco falso...
We're working very hard to find out where this virus came from, treat it...
Estamos tratando de descubrir el origen del virus para tratarlo...
and vaccinate against it if we can.
...y para desarrollar una vacuna.
We don't know all of that yet, we just don't.
No sabemos el origen.
What we do know is that in order to become sick...
Lo que sם sabemos es que para enfermarte...
you have to first come in contact with a sick person or something they touched.
...tienes que estar en contacto con un enfermo o con algo que tocף.
In order to get scared, all you have to do is come in contact with a rumor...
Para asustarte necesitas estar en contacto con un rumor...
television or the Internet.
...o con la televisiףn o con el Internet.
I think what Mr. Krumwiede is spreading is far more dangerous than the disease.
Lo que el seסor Krumwiede esparce es mבs peligroso que la enfermedad.
- Oh, really? - Yes.
- ¿De verdad? - Sם.
- That's funny. - What's funny?
- Quי gracioso. - ¿De quי habla?
You're funny, because if you check on Facebook...
Usted es gracioso. En Facebook hay un comunicado...
you'll find a communiqu attributed to Dr. Cheever by Elizabeth Nygaard...
...atribuido al doctor Cheever por Elizabeth Nygaard...
about the quarantine of Chicago hours before it was announced to the public.
...sobre la cuarentena de Chicago, horas antes de que fuera anunciada al pתblico.
That's why I think he's a bit disingenuous...
Por eso pienso que es falso...
when he says equal care for all and not just his friends.
...cuando habla de cuidado para todos, no solo para sus amigos.
Some pretty wild allegations here, Dr. Cheever.
Son acusaciones serias.
Can you tell us what communication appeared and when?
¿Quי comunicaciףn apareciף y dףnde?
What is the nature of your relationship with Nygaard?
¿Quי relaciףn tiene con Elizabeth Nygaard?
I'm not aware of anything attributed to me on any social network.
No sי de nada que se me atribuya en una red social.
I'm sure you're not. It is there. It is there.
Estoy seguro que no. ¡Pero ahם estב!
Tell them what an R-nought of two really means, Dr. Cheever.
Dםgales lo que significa un Ro de dos.
Teach them some math. Hm?
Ensיסeles un poco de matemבticas, ¿sם?
No? I'll do it.
¿No? Lo harי yo.
On day 1, there were two people with it, and then there were four.
El primer dםa, dos personas tenםan el virus y luego eran cuatro.
And then it was 16, and you think you've got it in front of you...
Y luego lo tenםan 16 y creםa que lo tenםa controlado.
but next it's 256, and then it's 65,000...
Pero luego son 256 y luego son 65000...
and it's behind you, above you, and all around you.
...y lo tiene detrבs y arriba y a su alrededor.
In 30 steps, it's a billion sick.
En 30 pasos, son mil millones de enfermos.
Three months. It's a math problem you can do on a napkin.
Tres meses. Se puede calcular en una servilleta.
And that's where we're headed.
Y vamos para allב.
And that's why you won't even tell us the number of the dead...
Y por eso ni nos dice el nתmero de muertos.
will you, Dr. Cheever?
¿Verdad, doctor Cheever?
But you'll tell your friends when to get out of Chicago...
Pero les dice a sus amigos que se vayan de Chicago...
before anyone else has a chance.
...antes que a nadie.
They're looking for a scapegoat.
Buscan un chivo expiatorio.
You just made it easy.
Les facilitף el trabajo.
The only reason we're not taking this to the attorney general...
La תnica razףn por la que no vamos a levantar cargos ahora...
is because we can't replace you right now.
...es porque no podemos reemplazarlo...
But there's gonna be an investigation. Do you understand that?
...pero habrב una investigaciףn. ¿Entiende?
And we don't wanna see you in front of the cameras anymore.
Ya no queremos verlo delante de las cבmaras.
- It's mutated. - Which way, better or worse?
- Ya mutף. - ¿Para bien o para mal?
It's moved into an African HIV AIDS population.
Penetrף en una poblaciףn africana de VIH y SIDA.
The Durban cluster is highly divergent.
El grupo de Durban es altamente divergente.
We have a new R-nought, Ellis. It's not two anymore.
Tenemos un nuevo Ro. Ya no es de dos.
I thought you said once we could grow it, we could vaccinate against it.
¿No dijiste que si lo podםamos cultivar, podםamos vacunar?
We tried using dead virus combined with atrophins to boost immune response.
Tratamos de usar virus muertos para estimular una reacciףn inmunolףgica.
And?
¿Y?
No protective antibodies, a lot of dead monkeys.
No hubo anticuerpos. Muchos monos murieron.
- Can you get to the good news? - Now we have to try a live attenuated virus.
- ¿Y la buena noticia? - Vamos a probar con un virus vivo.
- Like with polio? - Exactly.
- ¿Como con la polio? - Exacto.
The only danger with a live virus...
El תnico peligro con un virus vivo...
is the possibility that it will revert to wild type and kill the host.
...es que vuelva a su forma original y mate al huיsped.
And when will we know about that?
¿Cuבndo lo vamos a saber?
I'll ask the monkeys.
Le preguntarי a los monos.
As of right now, the mortality rate is fluctuating...
La tasa de mortalidad actual estב fluctuando entre el 25 y el 30%...
depending upon underlying medical conditions...
...dependiendo de males ya existentes...
socioeconomic factors, nutrition, fresh water.
...factores socioeconףmicos, comida, agua.
With the new mutation...
Con la nueva mutaciףn...
we are predicting an R-nought of no less than four.
...estamos prediciendo un Ro de no menos de cuatro.
And without a vaccine, we can anticipate...
Y sin una vacuna, podemos esperar que...
Folks, attention.
¡Atenciףn!
We appreciate your patience and we're doing the best we can.
Les agradecemos su paciencia y estamos haciendo todo lo posible.
We have exhausted our supply of meals ready-to-eat for today.
No tenemos mבs comidas preparadas hoy.
What?
- ¿Quי?
Please remain calm. We'll be sending--
Conserven la calma. Enviaremos...
Please-- Hey. Can we get some help over here?
Ayתdennos aquם.
Leave the park in an orderly fashion.
- Abandonen el parque en orden. - Ayתdame.
- You okay? - Thank you.
- ¿Estבs bien? - Gracias.
- Sorry, they got one of them. - Get the trucks!
- Se llevaron una. - ¡Vamos a los camiones!
Get the trucks!
¡Vamos a los camiones!
There's-- There's nothing in there!
¡Ahם no hay nada!
As the death toll in the United States is now believed...
Al llegar la cuenta de muertos en EE.UU. a los 2,5 millones...
the president issued a statement today from an undisclosed location...
...el presidente hablף desde un lugar desconocido...
implementing mandatory curfews in major metropolitan areas...
...e implementף toques de queda en בreas metropolitanas...
after a second consecutive day of riots in Dallas, Miami, Cleveland and Phoenix.
...despuיs de los tumultos en Dallas, Miami, Cleveland y Phoenix.
Absenteeism in law enforcement is nearing 25 percent...
El ausentismo en la policםa estב llegando al 25 por ciento...
according to reports--
...segתn los informes...
Because of the high volume of 911 calls...
Dado el volumen de llamadas a Urgencias, usen este directorio:
If you have symptoms, please hang up and call 612-188-6336.
Si tiene sםntomas, cuelgue y llame al 612-188-6336.
To report a death or for the removal of a body, please press 1.
Para reportar una muerte o recoger un cadבver, oprima 1.
Hello? Anybody home?
Hola. ¿Hay alguien en casa?
Hey, Mark?
¡Oye, Mark!
Hey, Jor?
¿Oye, Jor?
Jor?
¿Jor?
I can't feel my hands.
No siento mis manos.
That messed up my snow angel.
Arruinaste mi בngel de nieve.
I'm fine, Jory.
Estoy bien.
If neither of us have it, then we can't give it to each other.
Si ninguno de los dos lo tiene, no nos lo podemos pegar.
- Get away from her. - Dad!
- ¡Quםtate! - ¡Papב!
- Get away. Get away.
¡Alיjate! ¡Vete!
- What are you doing? - Stay there.
- ¿Quי haces? - ¡Quיdate ahם!
Go home, Andrew.
¡Vete a casa, Andrew!
Get up.
Levבntate.
Are we even close?
¿Ya falta poco?
If we even had a viable vaccine right now...
Si tuviיramos una vacuna viable ahora...
we would still have to do human trials, and that would take weeks.
...necesitarםamos pruebas humanas y tardarםan semanas.
And then we would have to get clearance and approval...
Luego hay que obtener la aprobaciףn...
figure out manufacturing and distribution.
...y empezar a fabricar y distribuir.
That would take months.
Eso lleva meses.
And then training survivors to give inoculations.
Luego entrenar a sobrevivientes para inocular.
More months, more deaths.
Mבs meses, mבs muertes.
Well, Homeland Security wants to know...
Seguridad Nacional quiere saber...
if we can put a vaccination in the water supply, like fluoride.
...si podemos poner la vacuna en el agua, como el flתor.
Cure everyone all at once.
¿Curar a todos a la vez?
I'm going home now, Ellis. It's getting late.
Me voy a casa, Ellis. Ya es tarde.
Merry Christmas.
Feliz Navidad.
- What are you doing? - It's okay, Dad.
- ¿Quי haces? - Estב bien, papב.
- No, it's not okay. - Do you remember Dr. Barry Marshall?
- No, no estב bien. - ¿Recuerdas al doctor Barry Marshall?
Thought that bacteria caused ulcers, not stress.
Creםa que las bacterias causaban תlceras, no el estrיs.
Gave himself the bug and then cured himself.
Se introdujo el microbio y se curף a sם mismo.
You taught me about him.
Tת me hablaste de יl.
I'm testing my vaccine.
Estoy probando mi vacuna.
No, this is different.
Esto es diferente.
I don't want to get you sick.
No quiero que te enfermes.
Ally, you can't take that chance.
No te puedes arriesgar.
Oh, Dad, you're here because you stayed in your practice...
Tת estבs aquם porque te quedaste en tu consultorio...
treating sick people after everyone else went home.
...tratando enfermos despuיs de que todos huyeron.
You took that chance. You took that chance every day.
Tת te arriesgaste. Te arriesgaste todos los dםas.
What?
¿Quי?
He won a Nobel Prize.
ֹl se ganף el premio Nobel.
- Yes, I know, Dad. - Barry Marshall.
- Sם, ya lo sי, papב. - Barry Marshall.
The Food and Drug Administration is accelerating approval...
El gobierno estב acelerando la aprobaciףn...
of the MEV-1 vaccine...
...de la vacuna MEv-1...
currently in production at five secret locations in the U.S. and Europe...
...que se estב produciendo...
saying the first doses could be available for human use within 90 days.
...diciendo que las primeras dosis estarבn listas en menos de 90 dםas.
The WHO estimates that it could take nearly a year...
La OMS calcula que puede tomar un aסo...
to manufacture and distribute the necessary amount of the vaccine...
...fabricar y distribuir bastantes vacunas...
to stop the spread of the virus...
...para parar la propagaciףn del virus...
which so far has taken over 26 million lives worldwide.
...que ha quitado mבs de 26 millones de vidas en el mundo.
But as labs work around the clock to produce the life-saving formula...
Pero mientras los laboratorios estבn produciendo la vacuna...
the question remains: Who gets it first?
...la pregunta sigue siendo: ¿quiיn la recibirב primero?
- Don't touch me. - Where is it?
- ¡No me toque! - ¿Dףnde estב?
- We don't have it. - Bullshit. He works there. He gets it first.
- No la tenemos. - ¡Mentira! ¡A יl le toca primero!
We don't have it. We have to wait--
¡No la tenemos! Tenemos que esper--
- Aubrey? - Ellis?
- ¿Aubrey? - ¿Ellis?
Where are you?
¿Dףnde estבs?
It's because they saw you on the news and they heard about what happened.
Te vieron en las noticias y oyeron lo que pasף.
- You all right? - They knew where you worked.
- ¿Estבs bien? - Sabםan dףnde trabajas.
They waited for you to leave.
Esperaron a que te fueras.
- Get up here. Come on. Let me look at you. - I tried to stop them.
- Levבntate. Dיjame verte. - Tratי de pararlos.
I tried.
Tratי.
- Did they touch you? Did they look sick? - They had masks on, Ellis, and gloves.
- ¿Te tocaron? ¿Se veםan enfermos? - Tenםan mבscaras, Ellis, y guantes.
Don't tell me that-- Aubrey, we get the vaccine tomorrow.
Aubrey, maסana nos dan la vacuna.
You have to trust me, Ellis.
Tienes que creerme.
They didn't touch me.
No me tocaron.
After the Spanish flu in 1918, you know, people got rich.
Despuיs de la gripe espaסola, en 1918, la gente se enriqueciף.
The Vicks VapoRub people, the Lysol people, look it up.
Los de Vicks VapoRub, los de Lysol. Investםgalo.
One man dies, another man makes money off his coffin.
Un hombre muere, el otro le vende un ataתd.
One country culls all their chickens, red meat goes into higher demand.
Un paםs mata a todos sus pollos, la carne de res sube de precio.
I'm not the first person to make money...
No soy el primero que gana dinero...
off the fact that our immune system is a work in progress.
...porque nuestro sistema inmunolףgico sigue cambiando.
The pharmaceutical industry do it every quarter.
La industria farmacיutica se beneficia cada trimestre.
I don't think anyone is immune to opportunity, Alan.
Todos aprovechamos una oportunidad, Alan.
It's just that studies show that there is no proof that forsythia works.
Pero los estudios no demuestran que la forsitia funciona.
Who conducted the studies?
¿Quiיn condujo los estudios?
What defines "works"? Against what strain of the virus?
¿Quי define si funciona? ¿Contra quי variedad del virus?
Did you know about the studies when we met the last time?
¿Sabםas de los estudios cuando nos vimos?
We can get in a lot of trouble--
Podemos meternos en lםos.
Do you really think this Dr. Hextall CDC person is Jesus in a lab coat?
¿Crees que la doctora Hextall es Jesתs en bata de laboratorio?
The government rushed the trials.
El gobierno acelerף las pruebas.
The lawyers indemnified the drug companies.
Los abogados indemnizaron a las compaסםas de medicamentos.
Maybe it causes autism or narcolepsy or cancer 10 years from now.
Quizב cause autismo o narcolepsia o cבncer dentro de diez aסos.
Who knows?
¿Quiיn sabe?
You-- The--
El...
The swine flu vaccine killed people back in 1976.
La vacuna de la gripe porcina matף a gente en 1976.
Nerve disease.
Enfermedades nerviosas.
So we're all guinea pigs, starting from today.
Todos somos conejillos de Indias.
Just wait, they'll start listing side effects like the credits at the end of a movie.
Van a enumerar los efectos secundarios uno tras otro.
People trust you, Alan. If you tell them not to take it--
La gente confםa en ti. Si les dices que no la tomen...
That's right.
Asם es.
They trust me. All 12 million unique visitors.
La gente confםa en mם. Mis 12 millones de visitantes.
I'm a trusted man stepping up to a microphone...
Soy un hombre de confianza...
in front of a very large crowd.
...hablando delante de una multitud.
That's who I am. That's the brand.
Ese soy yo. Esa es la marca.
I say the right thing, nobody shows up for their shot.
Si digo lo correcto, nadie se vacuna.
Maybe they'd rather roll the dice with forsythia.
Quizב prefieran tomar forsitia.
I can make that happen.
Yo puedo hacer que eso pase.
I just wanna know I'm in the best position possible when I do.
Pero quiero estar en buena posiciףn.
What does that mean, exactly?
¿Quי significa eso, exactamente?
If I'm gonna step into the crosshairs, I wanna know what's in--
Si me voy a poner en la mira, quiero saber quי es...
- Is he with you? - What? Who?
- ¿ֹl vino contigo? - ¿Quי? ¿Quiיn?
Are you wearing a wire?
¿Traes un micrףfono?
Alan, I didn't have a choice. They've seen your blog.
No tuve mבs remedio. Vieron tu blog.
Get him.
Detente.
- Far enough, far enough. - For what? Tell me, for what?
- Basta, alto. - ¿Por quי? Dםgame, ¿por quי?
Securities fraud, conspiracy, and most likely manslaughter.
Por fraude, conspiraciףn y, probablemente, homicidio.
- It cured me. Forsythia cured me. - We'll see, Alan.
- Me curף. La forsitia me curף. - Ya lo veremos.
This is entrapment.
Esto es un delito.
You can't take my blood. You can't, that's my property.
No pueden tomar mi sangre. Es propiedad privada.
We may never know where this disease came from.
Quizב nunca sepamos el origen de esta enfermedad.
But we do know that this vaccine is the result...
Pero sם sabemos que esta vacuna se debe...
of the courage and perseverance of a remarkable few.
...al valor y la persistencia de unas cuantas personas notables.
We shall now begin the drawing. John.
Vamos a iniciar el sorteo.
The first MEV-1 vaccination...
La primera vacuna de MEV-1...
are those people born on March 10th.
...la recibirב la gente que naciף el 10 de marzo.
March 10th.
El 10 de marzo.
We remind all of you to stay 10 feet apart from each other...
Les recuerdo a todos que se coloquen a intervalos de tres metros...
while on line.
...en la fila.
Shouldn't you be downstairs?
- ¿No deberםas estar allב abajo? - Estoy rastreando lotes de vacunas.
This is what you have to be doing right this minute?
¿Lo tienes que hacer en este momento?
This is what I want to do right this minute.
Esto es lo que quiero hacer en este momento.
Take a bow, Ally.
Recibe tus aplausos.
People have for a lot less.
Hay quienes los reciben por mucho menos.
It's not that hard to give yourself an injection.
No es tan difםcil inyectarse uno solo.
What about Mears or my father or you?
¿Y quי tal Mears, o mi padre, o tת?
I'm gonna take a bow while you get hauled in front of Congress?
¿Voy a recibir aplausos mientras te juzgan a ti?
What do I say when they ask about that?
¿Quי les digo cuando me pregunten?
You tell them that I told a loved one who told a loved one...
Que le dije a alguien que amo...
and that I'd do it again.
...y que lo volverםa a hacer.
Without you-- Ally, you have saved millions of lives.
Sin ti, Ally... Salvaste millones de vidas.
That's a great story. It also happens to be true.
Es una gran historia y es verםdica.
Now, how often can you say that?
Eso no pasa a menudo.
The next citizens to receive the MEV-1 vaccination...
Los siguientes ciudadanos que van a recibir la vacuna...
are those born on the date...
...son los nacidos en...
What is that? January 11th.
¿Quי fecha? El 11 de enero.
Okay. All right, 144.
Todavםa faltan 144.
That's-- There's still, uh, 200--
Aתn faltan 200...
More than 200 birthdays, hon, that haven't been called, so that's good.
Mבs de 200 cumpleaסos que no han salido.
That's a good number.
Y eso es bueno.
- What if they run out? - They're not gonna run out.
- ¿Y si se acaba? - No se va a acabar.
They have enough to keep up with demand. They said that already.
Tienen bastante para aguantar la demanda.
Maybe I'm immune like you and I don't even need it.
Quizב sea inmune como tת y ni la necesito.
That's not a chance we're gonna take.
No me voy a arriesgar.
So instead we lose spring, we lose summer...
Asם que perdemos la primavera, perdemos el verano...
we lose another 144 days that don't happen again.
...perdemos otros 144 dםas que no van a regresar.
Why can't they invent a shot that keeps time from passing?
¿Por quי no inventan vacunas para que no pase el tiempo?
It's gonna start getting normal again, Jory.
Todo va a volver a la normalidad.
How do you call this, "fish," in Chinese?
¿Cףmo se dice "pez" en chino?
This is y.
Esto es yת.
- This is beautiful. - Thank you.
- Te saliף hermoso. - Gracias.
It's time. We have to run. He just landed.
Ya es hora. Tenemos que irnos. Acaba de aterrizar.
I want you to keep drawing...
Quiero que sigan dibujando.
and Assand will come and finish the class, all right?
Assand va a venir a terminar la clase. ¿Estב bien?
I'll see you soon.
Nos vemos muy pronto.
- See you.
- Nos vemos.
Tsuen Wan Cemetery off the Number 3 Expressway.
Cementerio Tsuen Wan, por la carretera 3.
It's close to where you are now. In 15 minutes.
Cerca de donde estב ahora. En 15 minutos.
One hundred doses. Nobody from the ministry, no police.
Cien dosis. No debe haber nadie del ministerio, ni policםas.
If we see anybody else, any other vehicles, you'll never see her again.
Si vemos a alguien mבs o un auto, no la volverב a ver.
Yes?
¿Sם?
Yes, I'm fine. Please give them what they ask.
Estoy bien. Deles lo que piden.
I just wanna go home.
Quiero irme a casa.
Once we have the vaccine, we'll tell you where to find her.
En cuanto tengamos las vacunas le diremos dףnde encontrarla.
- Is it French or American? - We could not get enough from the French.
- ¿Son francesas o estadounidenses? - Habםa pocas francesas.
It's been made here. The same formula, though.
Son de aquם, con la misma fףrmula.
It is effective, I promise.
Es efectiva, se lo juro.
There, be careful.
Tome. Tenga cuidado.
Wait, where is she?
¿Dףnde estב ella?
- We don't know what it is. - Well, we have no choice.
- No sabemos quי es esto. - No tenemos mבs remedio.
Where is Dr. Orantes?
¿Dףnde estב la doctora Orantes?
Now, wait, this is not what we agreed on.
¡Esperen! ¡Esto no fue lo que acordamos!
Are you okay?
¿Estבs bien?
Yes, I'm fine.
Sם.
I'm good.
Estoy bien.
Oh, I almost forgot.
Por poco se me olvida.
- What's that? - Your vaccine.
- ¿Quי es esto? - Tu vacuna.
The one you took was a placebo.
La que tomaste era un placebo.
What?
¿Quי?
The Chinese insisted. There have been many abductions, not just here.
Los chinos insistieron. Ha habido muchos secuestros, no solo aquם.
In Russia, Mexico, all over.
En Rusia, en Mיxico.
Government officials, scientists, or Westerners with great wealth.
Oficiales del gobierno, cientםficos, occidentales ricos.
Mostly perpetrated by organized crime or revolutionary groups...
Cometidos por revolucionarios o la mafia...
trying to extort medicines.
...para obtener medicinas.
The Chinese don't negotiate with kidnappers. It wasn't up to us.
Los chinos no negocian con secuestradores.
We've got a limited supply, just like everyone else.
Tenemos pocas vacunas, igual que todos.
Leo-- Leonora.
¡Leonora!
Where are you going?
¿Adףnde vas?
Blood results came back, Mr. Krumwiede.
Ya regresaron sus pruebas de sangre.
You never had the virus. You have no antibodies. You lied.
Nunca tuvo el virus. No tiene anticuerpos. Usted mintiף.
Of course that's what your labs say.
Por supuesto que eso dice su laboratorio.
Forsythia is a lie.
Lo de la forsitia es una mentira.
It's a lie, and you made $4.5 million for telling it.
Es una mentira y usted ganף 4,5 millones de dףlares con ella.
You wanna blog about that?
Escriba sobre eso.
You are going to go away, Mr. Krumwiede, and so is all your money.
Usted va a desaparecer y su dinero tambiיn.
I can't even imagine all the civil suits people are gonna file against you...
No me imagino cuבntas demandas le van a levantar...
and I have a pretty good imagination.
...y tengo buena imaginaciףn.
Now you wanna tell people not to get vaccinated...
Ahora le quiere decir a la gente que no se vacune...
when that's the best chance they've got.
...cuando eso la puede salvar.
If I could throw your computer in jail, I would.
Yo meterםa a su computadora en la cבrcel.
Made bail.
Pagaron su fianza.
Are we done here?
¿Ya terminamos?
Evidently, there are 12 million other people as crazy as you are.
Parece que hay 12 millones de personas tan locas como usted.
You made bail. Congratulations.
Pagaron su fianza. Felicidades.
Cheever and wife. Congratulate Aubrey for me.
Cheever y su esposa. Felicite a Aubrey.
I'd shake your hand, but I don't wanna set a bad example.
No le darי la mano para no dar un mal ejemplo.
and we really hope you can be with us.
Esperamos que nos pueda acompaסar.
Sure. So are you ready for yours? I've got mine.
Claro. ¿Listo para su vacuna? Yo ya me vacunי.
No, I think she's gonna wanna do these together.
No. Ella quiere que nos las pongamos juntos.
- I know she sprang for some champagne. - Hm.
Comprף champaסa.
They have scheduled the hearings. We'll both be expected to testify.
Ya dieron fecha para la audiencia. Los dos vamos a testificar.
Right.
Bien.
Good luck.
Buena suerte.
Head back, Anthony.
La cabeza hacia atrבs.
There you go.
Eso es.
Good job.
Muy bien.
I can't give him the bracelet, but at least you know he'll be safe.
No le puedo dar el brazalete, pero al menos sabes que estב a salvo.
Yeah, beats waiting another seven months.
Sם. Es mejor que esperar otros siete meses.
Okay, what do you say?
¿Quי se dice?
- Thank you. - You're welcome, Anthony.
- Gracias. - De nada, Anthony.
You know where this comes from, shaking hands?
¿Sabes de dףnde viene lo de darse la mano?
No.
No.
It was a way of showing a stranger you weren't carrying a weapon in the old days.
Era la manera de mostrarle a un extraסo que no estabas armado.
- Good job. Now go finish your homework. - Okay.
- Muy bien. Ve a terminar tu tarea. - Ya voy.
Yeah.
Sם.
You offered your empty right hand to show that you meant no harm.
Ofrecםas la mano vacםa para mostrar que no tenםas mala intenciףn.
- Oh, I didn't know that. - I wonder if the virus does.
- No lo sabםa. - ¿Lo sabrב el virus?
Well, Dr. Cheever, thanks.
Gracias, doctor Cheever.
Take care, Roger.
Cuםdate, Roger.
You too.
Usted tambiיn.
You're not gonna get in trouble for this, are you?
¿Esto no te va a causar problemas?
Will you be quiet?
Cבllate.
My number is 287, Ellis.
Mi nתmero es el 287, Ellis.
If we weren't married, I'd have to wait almost a year.
Sino estuviיramos casados, esperarםa casi un aסo.
Then it's a good thing we're married.
Menos mal que nos casamos.
Hold your head back.
La cabeza hacia atrבs.
I don't wanna give them another reason to go after you.
No quiero darles otra razףn para acusarte.
Will you please be quiet and hold your head back?
Deja de hablar. Inclina la cabeza hacia atrבs.
Okay, go.
Bien. Inhala.
And go.
E inhala.
Good.
Bien.
All right.
Muy bien.
Like you said, baby...
Como tת dijiste, nena...
just taking care of everybody that's in my lifeboat.
...estoy cuidando a todos los que estבn en mi bote salvavidas.
Dad, are you coming?
¡Papב! ¿Ya vienes?
Yep.
¡Sם!
I'm just looking for the camera.
Estoy buscando la cבmara.